But I am a first year
master's student from the University of—
National University of Singapore,
and the paper I'm presenting today
will be sort of part of that work,
a paper
that I wrote for independent study.
So I will
now share my screen.
Okay.
Can everyone see this?
Okay, great.
So I'll just start.
Thank you for coming.
Today I will present my paper titled
“Reverse Pleasure: A Defense of Difficulty
Without Resolution.” And I'll sort of
break this down into three parts.
The first where I will define
what I mean by difficulty, and the second
addressing the problem of pleasure
and how it interacts with difficulty.
And then the third, I will sort of examine
icepick largest game, Pathologic Classic
HD, as a kind of case study to show
how pleasure might arise from what I call
difficulty,
focusing mainly on two aspects of the game
how it deals with narrative
and how it deals with time.
Okay,
so just to start with a broad definition
of what I'm talking about
or with regards to difficulty,
the OED [Oxford English Dictionary]
gives difficulty as a subject that
needs much effort or skill to accomplish,
deal with, or understand a thing.
And so, from just this broad definition,
we can already see how
subjective and evaluative the term is,
where a lot of factors contribute
to whether a player finds a game
difficult or not, and the debate between
what should be considered too difficult
seems almost perennial.
Like the release of song, for example,
I think is just one
in the latest string of games
that get embroiled in quite polarized
cultural discussions
surrounding difficulty.
And these discussions typically center
around mechanical difficulty,
which Patrick Jagoda defines
as the required familiarity
with the design system
and a cultivation of skills that
let you achieve success or mastery.
But there are other types of difficulty
as well,
such as interpretive and affective.
And so my sort of project
will focus on, well,
the intermix between the three of them,
but mainly on the second two,
and how we justify difficulty in games
and art in general,
because when playing a game, it's
sort of hard
to isolate one aspect from the rest.
And you you have to consider all of them
in holistically.
And also when we sort of discuss
difficulty in both the public
and academic sphere is often
not just about what
the purpose of difficult art is,
but often touches on additional issues
of accessibility,
aural intention, gamer culture, and so on.
So the central question of my research
project is basically
what is the purpose of difficulty?
Is it a productive quality
or a barrier to entry?
Are those
the only two ways of thinking about it?
Like,
what other possibilities could difficulty
open up for us
in terms of thinking about aims?
Okay, so I'll move on to part two.
Addressing the problem of pleasure.
And I call it a problem
because it's kind of a hard thing to pin
down, more so than difficulty,
I think, as most affects are.
Leonard Diepeveen, on his work
in On Modernist Difficulty, describes it
as this like grand but ghostly presence
that disappears under critical attention,
and the connection
between pleasure and difficulty,
however, has been sort of proven
by certain scholars.
Jesper Juul, in his book
called The Art of Failure, examines
what he calls the paradox of failure,
where players actively seek out failure
even though it gives them
negative emotion,
and he saw resolves this paradox
by showing how difficulty and failure
make the eventual victory
more pleasurable when it is overcome.
And when I was reading that, I sort of
had it as analogous to the perspective of
the work of interpretation in literature,
where, like certain criticism,
often centers around finding a like a key
to understanding a text
or like a reading strategy or framework
that makes the text mean something.
And so a difficult text sort of forces
the reader or critic
to think of alternate ways
to make the text cohere, and it becomes
like this productive force
that has to be overcome.
And so to return
back to the context of games,
like even in the case of, say,
like walking simulators,
part of the pleasure,
I think, comes from unveiling
what happens next through player action,
even if that action is
just as simple as walking from point A
to point B to seek out the narrative.
And so in all of these cases,
pleasure comes from making progress,
from resolving the difficulty,
whether that be like overcoming
like a difficult level,
or finding some sort of interpretation
that makes a difficult
text more easy to understand.
So, however, there are some exceptions
to this line of thinking.
And here I'll mention Bo Ruberg,
who whose work on no-fun games
reframes the way we think of play,
and questions like normative assumptions
about what having fun even means and what
the purpose of games and play really is.
And while they are, approach
comes from the opposite end of this
like difficulty pleasure equation,
I think we both land
on around the same insights,
which is that pleasure can be found
not just in progress,
but in resistance and deferred
satisfaction as well.
Okay, so in this essay,
The Pleasure of the Text,
literary theorist Roland Barthes attempts
to locate this particular
type of what I'm calling
perverse pleasure by describing
what he calls the text of bliss.
And he says it is the text
that imposes a state of loss,
a text that discomfort unsettles
the readers historical,
cultural, psychological assumptions,
the consistency of his tastes,
values, memories, and brings to a crisis
his relation with language.
In his essay, he distinguishes
between these texts and what he calls
texts of pleasure,
which are the texts that content the grant
euphoria, the text that comes from culture
and does not break from it.
And so in throughout his work,
he sort of continuously circles
around a particular poetics of pleasure.
But I don't think he ever quite manages
the workout precisely what
this sort of bliss entails,
or how it emerges from the reader's
experience of discomfort.
And in the end,
he sort of forced to conclude that
no thesis on the pleasure of text,
the text is possible.
And yet, in spite of everything,
the text gives me bliss.
And so, while pleasure for him
retains that grand but ghostly presence,
it is through this declaration of failure
that I think the pleasure of the text
becomes itself a text of bliss,
a text that, through its omissions,
its rhetorical complexity,
its contradictions and obsessions,
demonstrates Barthes's argument
not so much through the content
as the method
by which he chooses to present it,
and so he shows that difficulty
and bliss are indeed intertwined.
But the interests of bliss occurs
in the uttering
and not in the sequence of utterances.
So, in other words,
it's in the process of experiencing
a difficult text
that the pleasure is found.
And I think that's particularly the case
for video games,
which since, like the uttering,
typically involves a higher amount
of embodiment
than a literary like novel, for example.
Okay,
so to that end, I'll now try to examine
my experience
of playing Pathologic Classic HD.
Henceforth,
I will refer to it as Pathologic
and examine the ways in which
difficulty in that game can be considered
irresponsible in the ways
in which this bliss
arises from that difficulty.
So just a brief, short
background on the game.
It was initially released in Russia
under the title Moore, Utopia
and then was rereleased twice.
So Classic HD,
which I played, was the second
English translated release of the game,
and I think translation would probably be
another layer of difficulty
on top of everything else, but
there's probably not time to go into that,
so I'll just focus on two
aspects of the game.
The first being narrative,
which is unveiled over
the course of three
intersecting playable routes.
Each playable character
has their own background and access
to different types of information,
and each has 12 in-game days to attempt
to save a fictional Russian town
for being overrun
by this mysterious sand plague.
So in order to save as many townspeople
as possible
and stay alive in the process,
the player must sort of piece together
a narrative through conversations
with various NPCs, and each MPC
has their own backstories,
motivations, biases, blind spots.
They can lie to you.
And so dialog is often both
quite obtuse and misleading,
and a player can spend hours
wandering aimlessly through the town
if they fail to follow a quest,
or they picked the wrong dialog option
that foreclosed the quest altogether.
And because they can lie to you,
each conversation
becomes a struggle
in understanding, in interpretation.
And it's this continuous
process of interpretation
that lies at the heart of Pathologic
gameplay, and is both what makes the game
so compelling and simultaneously,
what makes it so difficult,
because its construction
of narrative poses
real interpretive and affective challenges
that then later affect how difficult
the game is mechanically as well.
Okay.
And then the other aspect,
the major aspect of the game
is how it constructs time.
So you have 12 in-game days each in game
day is about two hours real time.
And certain quests require you
to be in certain places as specific times.
There is no running mechanics,
so most of the game will be spent
walking around from point
A to point B, backtracking a lot
through locations that you've probably
already been to in the same day,
and a large part of navigating the town,
even though you might have gone through
the same spot multiple times, it's
still not something you can do mindlessly.
Because as the days progress
and the plague worsens,
you have things like marauders, soldiers,
rats, roving clouds of play
that sort of appear and disappear
at random in infected districts.
So you kind of got to pay attention
and avoid those.
Fighting in the game
is quite clunky and costly,
and usually the safest option
is to just take a longer route
to avoid these districts or dangers
altogether.
And the effect of all that
is that time in the game feels often
like it's moving both too fast
and too slow because of boredom
of backtracking across the same streets
is cut with the anxiety of the knowledge
that death is always around every corner
and the clock is always running down.
Other than reading dialog
and the occasional fight,
which you often will die
in, walking is the bulk of how you spend
your time in the game, and in some ways
is kind of the game itself.
Like to cut it out entirely by, say,
introducing a mod that obviously to run,
but really to be removing to
to remove like a vital part
of the effective experience.
Okay, so this is just a screenshot
that I took
while playing the game to show both show
like the visuals of the game,
and also to sort of
make the point that the aesthetic
of the game also contribute heavily
to how effectively difficult
it is, because you have this consistent,
murky palette throughout that you're
sort of seeing all the time,
and it gets exhausting after a while.
Okay,
so I'm nearing the end of my presentation.
There's a bit of a spoiler alert
because I will now
talk about how I felt
after playing the end of the game.
So at the end of my playthrough
through “The Bachelor” route,
which is one of the characters,
there were three endings that I could
choose from.
I could either save the town
and destroy the Polyhedron,
which is that little bit
coming out from the rock.
It's like a magical building.
Too much to explain.
Just know that it was kind of important
throughout the story,
so I could either save the town
and destroy the Polyhedron, or
destroy the town and save the Polyhedron,
or let both be overrun by the plague.
And no matter which ending I chose,
like when I went back to reload
to see what the ending was,
it was all delivered through this sort of
like highly theatricalized
Silent Place thing, where the town
was extracted into a model of the town
like a rock, and the players
and the NPCs that you had been interacting
with sort of all silently
reacted with their really uncanny valley
looking expressions.
And after 30 hours
and I think more close to 37 hours
of like, struggling through this game,
these endings all felt kind of flat to me.
There was no sense of narrative closure.
My satisfaction was, I felt,
infinitely deferred.
I couldn't get any sort of pleasure
from that experience
of like having the story
finally come to a close.
And yet, after finishing the game,
I was still left thinking about it
long after it had the credits rolled.
And I think part of the reason why
it was so impactful to me
was a combination
of experiencing the game.
so it was
like a combination of experiencing
the game and its unresolvable difficulty.
I think that drove my fascination with it
and transformed my pleasure
into something
that was not grand, but ghostly,
but something
real with and that had teeth.
Okay.
In closing, that was my paper.
This work is a part of my master's
thesis, which is so in progress.
So along with the questions,
I would appreciate any feedback
or suggestions for further reading,
or like games that are in the same pocket
as Pathologic,
or do interesting things with difficulty.
Thank you.